The narrator of Passage I describes the behavior Of his friend Jerry, with whom he is rooming in an unspecified African country. In Passage 2, a different narrator describes himself while visiting an English couple in London. Both fictional works were published in the early 1980's.
Passage 1. Jerry was deceitful, but at the time I did not think he was imaginative enough to do any damage. And yet his was not the conventional double life that most White people led in Africa. Jerry had certain ambitions: ambition makes more liars than egotism does. But Jerry was so careful, his lies such modest calculations, that he was always believed. He said he was from Boston. "Belmont actually," he told me, when I said I was from Medford. His passport said Watertown. He felt he had to conceal it. That explained a lot: the insecurity of living on the lower slopes of the long hill, between the smoldering steeples of Boston and the clean, high-priced air of Belmont. We are probably no more class-conscious than the British, but when we make class an issue, it seems more than snobbery. It becomes a bizarre spectacle, a kind of attention-seeking, and I can- not hear an American speaking of his or her social position without thinking. of a human fly, one of those tiny people in grubby, capes whom one sometimes sees clinging to the brickwork of a tall building. What had begun as fantasy had, after six months of his repeating it in our insignificant place, made it seem like fact. I had the impression that it was one of the reasons Jerry wanted to stay in Africa. If you tell enough lies about your- self, they take hold. It becomes impossible ever to go back, since that means facing the truth. In Africa, no one could dispute what Jerry said he was: a wealthy Bostonian, from a family of some distinction, adventuring in philanthropy before inheriting his father's business.
Passage 2. Anna and Chris made me at ease the first day in their polished living room though I was not sure why these people would bother putting themselves out for me at all. And when they kept inviting me back for dinner parties and extending their hospitality, I wondered if maybe they were bored, or if their ignorance of American types was such that they. failed to see that I was not at all of their social class: I kept expecting some crude regional expression to betray me; and, once I thought of it in those terms, I knew I would have to make sure they saw that side. of me to do less would be like trying to "pass." Yet whatever I said seemed to make no difference in their acceptance. I then suspected that my rough-edgedness itself was entertaining to them as a source of vitality, their diversion-of-the-month. This would have made more sense if the Hodgkinsons were bored, dried-up people who needed to feast on any new stranger, but they were not; they were in the world and leading stimulating lives and I finally had to come to the anxious conclusion that they simply liked me. The truth was I had changed, though I was perhaps the last to see it. While still feeling myself a child from the slums, I had gotten a university education, acquired a taste for esoteric culture; and now, when I thought back to my students in East Harlem, where I felt I should really belong, it seemed that I was a stranger there as well. Yet I did not fit in with people born to middle-class comfort either. It seemed there was no group at all in which I could feel at home. Perhaps anyone with the tiniest sensitivity comes to that basal, conclusion. But what I was seeing now with horror, in the accepting eyes of those a class above me, was that . I had already partly/metamorphosed—into them. My only hope of growing seemed to point in an upward social direction; but that direction aroused in me a characteristic disapproval and distaste. I was by no means attracted by everything I saw in well-off people's lives, and the momentary need to accept their hospitality and keep secret my criticism of them made me feel like a hypocrite.


