 The following passage appeared in an essay written in 1987 in which the author, who is of Native American descent, examines the representation of Native Americans during the course of United States history. In many respects living Native Americans remain as mysterious, exotic, and unfathomable to their contemporants at the end of the twentieth century as they were to the Pilgrim settlers over three hundred fifty years ago. 
Native rights, motives, customs, languages, and aspirations are misunderstood by Euro-Americans out of a culpable ignorance that is both self-serving and self-righteous. Part of the problem may well stem from the long-standing tendency of European or Euro-American thinkers to regard Native Americans as fundamentally and profoundly different, motivated more often by mysticism than by ambition, charged more by unfathomable visions than by intelligence or introspection. This idea is certainly not new. Rousseau's "noble savages" wandered, pure of heart, through a pristine world. Since native people were simply assumed to be incomprehensible, they were seldom comprehended. Their societies were simply beheld, often through cloudy glasses, and rarely probed by the tools of logic and deductive analysis automatically reserved for cultures prejudged to be "civilized." And on those occasions when Europeans did attempt to formulate an encompassing theory, it was not, ordinarily, on a human-being-to-human-being basis, but rather through an ancestor-descendant model. Native Americans, though obviously contemporary with their observers, were somehow regarded as ancient, examples of what Stone Age Europeans must have been like. It's a great story, an international crowd pleaser, but there is a difficulty: Native Americans were, and are, Homo sapiens sapiens. Though often equipped with a shovel-shaped incisor tooth, eyes with epicanthic folds, or an extra molar cusp, Native American people have had to cope, for the last forty thousand years or so, just like everyone else. Their cultures have had to make internal sense, their medicines have had to work consistently and practically, their philosophical explanations have had to be reasonably satisfying and dependable, or else the ancestors reasonably satisfying and dependable, or else the ancestors of those now called Native Americans would truly have vanished long ago. The reluctance in accepting this obvious fact comes from the Eurocentric conviction that the West holds a monopoly on science, logic, and clear thinking. To admit that other, culturally divergent viewpoints are equally plausible is to cast doubt on the monolithic i center of Judeo-Christian belief: that there is but one of everything God, right way, truth and Europeans alone knew what that was. If Native American cultures were acknowledged as viable, then European societies were something less than an exclusive club. It is little wonder, therefore, that Native Americans were perceived not so much as they were but as they had to be, from a European viewpoint. They dealt in magic, not method. They were stuck in their past, not guided by its precedents.
 Such expedient misconception argues strongly for the development and dissemination of a more accurate, more objective historical account of native peoples a goal easier stated than accomplished. Native American societies were nonliterate before and during much of the early period of their contact with Europe, making the task of piecing together a history particularly demanding. The familiar an reassuring kinds of written documentation found in Europe societies of equivalent chronological periods do not exist, and the forms of tribal record preservation available oral history, tales, mnemonic devices, and religious rituals strike university-trained academics as inexact, unreliable, and suspect. Western historians, culture-bound by their own approach to knowledge, are apt to declaim that next to nothing, save the evidence of archaeology, can be known of early Native American life. To them, an absolute void is more acceptable and rigorous than an educated guess. However, it is naive to assume that any culture's history is perceived without subjective prejudice. Every modern observer, whether he or she was schooled in the traditions of the South Pacific or Zaire, of Hanover, New Hampshire, or Vienna, Austria, was exposed at an early age to one or another form of folklore about Native Americans. For some, the very impressions about Native American tribes that initially attracted them to the field of American history are aspects most firmly rooted in popular myth and stereo- type. Serious scholarship about Native American culture and history is unique in that it requires an initial, 'abrupt, and wrenching demythologizing. Most students do not start d wrenching demythologizing. Most students do not start from point zero, but from minus zero, and in the process are often required to abandon cherished childhood fantasies of superheroes or larger-than-life villains. 

 