The following passage is excerpted from a review of a book about aviation's early years. Aviation belonged to the new,century in part because the engineering that went into flying machines was utterly different from that of the Industrial Revolution. Nineteenth-century engineering revolved around the steam engine. It was about weight and brute power—beautifully machined heavy steel, burnished bronze, polished copper pipes, ornamental cast iron—everything built, with no expense spared, to withstand great pressures and last any number of lifetimes. Airplane construction was the opposite of all that; it was about lightness. it was about lightness. The Wright brothers, who created one of the first airplanes, started out making bicycles, which were all the rage at the turn of the century. They knew about thin-wall steel tubes, wire-spoked wheels, chain drives, and whatever- else it took to construct efficient machines that weighed as little as possible. In effect, they were practical engineers at the cheap end of the market, but they happened to be t the cheap end of the market, but they happened to be fascinated by flight. Says one writer, "Wilbur [Wright] spent his time studying the flight of vultures, eagles, ospreys, and hawks, trying to discover the secret of their ability to maneuver with their wings in unstable air. To those who later asked him how he learned to fly, he loved to reply through his scarcely opened lips: 'Like a bird.'" This is the point at which engineering intersects with the imagination, with humanity's ancient dream of freeing itself from gravity. Until the first fliers got to work, the body was earthbound, but it enclosed a soul that flew in meditation, in poetry, and, as the seventeenth-century English poet Andrew Marvell showed, sometimes spectacularly in both:
 Casting the body's vest aside My soul into the boughs does glide: There, like a Bird, it sits and sings, Then whets and combs its silver wings, And, till prepared for longer flight, Waves in its plumes the various light.
 At the beginning of this century, the new light engineering that allowed people to fly seemed to the uninitiated a kind of poetry. In 1913, a writer in the Atlantic Monthly claimed that "machinery is our new art form" and praised "the engineers whose poetry is too deep to look poetic" and whose gifts "have swung their souls free . . . like gods." One of Wright's most eloquent admirers called him a poet and compared him to one of "those monks of Asia Minor who live perched on the tops of inaccessible mountain peaks. The soul of Wilbur Wright is just as high and faraway." Wright was, in fact, "deeply middle-class and unheroic," writes one biographer, but those obsessed with the glamour of flight pretended not to notice. 