Sometimes the meaning of old phrases is self-evident, as with to move like greased lightning and a close shave. But quite often we are left with language that seems to have sprung out of the blue and does not appear to signify anything in particular—even steven, fit as a fiddle, or to pain! the town red Explanations are frequently posited but are too often unpersuasive. One popular dictionary, for example, suggests that to be joshing might be connected to example, suggests that to be joshing might be connected to the humorist Josh Billings, but in fact the term was current as early as 1845. Josh Billings was unknown outside his t as early as 1845. Josh Billings was unknown outside his neighborhood until 1860.