The intelligence of dolphins is well documented by science. Studies show that dolphins are able to understand sign language, solve puzzles, and use objects in their environment as tools. Scientists also believe that dolphins possess a sophisticated language: numerous instances have been recorded in which dolphins transmitted information from one individual to another. A recent experiment proved that dolphins can even recognize themselves in a mirror something achieved by very few animals. This behavior demonstrates that dolphins are aware of their own individuality, indicating a level of intelligence that may be very near our own.
Are dolphins unusually intelligent? Dolphins have large brains, but we know that brain size alone does not determine either the nature or extent of intelligence. Some researchers have suggested that dolphins have big brains because they need them for sonar and sound processing and for social interactions. Others have argued that regardless of brain size, dolphins have an intelligence level somewhere between that of a dog and a chimpanzee. The fact is, we don't know, and comparisons may not be especially helpful. Just as human intelligence is appropriate for human needs, dolphin intelligence is right for the dolphin's way of life. Until we know more, all we can say is that dolphin intelligence is different.